# Justin Mayer

Ph.D. Candidate in Materials, UC Santa Barbara engineering.ucsb.edu/jmayer

#### Education

#### UC Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara, CA

2019-Present

Ph.D. Candidate, Materials Department, University of California, Santa Barbara Advisors: Professor Ram Seshadri and Professor Tresa M. Pollock

#### Northeastern University, Boston, MA

2014 - 2018

Bachelor of Science, Degree in Chemical Engineering & Physics; Minor in Mathematics

## Research Summary

My research examines the relationships between atomic order, microstructure, and magnetism. I am particularly interested in applying multiscale modeling to outstanding problems in magnetism and plasticity. I perform atomistic calculations *via* density functional theory to inform phase field caluclations at the mesoscopic level. I am also particularly interested in code development. Specifically, I aid in the modification and maintenance of the phase field dislocation dynamics software of Professor Irene J. Beyerlein's research group.

## **Professional Experience**

#### HRL Laboratories, Malibu, CA

Materials Researcher

January 2019–August 2019

- · Applied the grain refinement technology from initial co-op to additional unweldable alloy systems
- · Designed and characterized a novel solid-state device for sourcing and sinking alkali vapor
- Developed Matlab scripts to analyze x-ray computed tomography measurements of a ceramic composite
   Undergraduate Co-op
   May 2016—December 2016
- · Performed electroless Ni-P plating for thermal barrier coating of piston crowns
- · Studied the potential to refine grain structure of 3D printed aluminum alloys
- · Filed invention disclosure on a novel precursor material to be used in future welding processes

#### Dipartimento di Fisica, Universitá degli Studi di Milano, Milan, Italy

Research Assistant

July 2017–December 2017

- · Prepared gold nanoparticles embedded in amorphous silicon through DC magnetron sputtering
- · Characterized amorphous silicon grown on gold nanoparticles via X-ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy

# Mefford Magnetic & Nanostructured Materials Research Group, Clemson, SC Research Assistant May 2015–July 2015

· Studied the binding properties of different polymer end groups to the surface of nanoparticles

- · Quantified ligand exchange activity of iron oxide nanoparticles with liquid scintillation counting

# **Teaching**

Northeastern University

Physics I and Physics II Peer Tutor; Founder of Physics II peer tutoring program

Undergraduate teaching assistant for Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics I

#### **Publications**

- 12. B. E. Rhodes, **J. A. Mayer**, Y. M. Eggeler, S. Xu, J. D. Lamb, J. Wendorf, M. P. Echlin, J. Li, T. M. Pollock, R. Seshadri, I. J. Beyerlein, and D. S. Gianola, Deformation mechanisms and defect structures in Heusler intermetallics, *In preparation*.
- 11. **J. A. Mayer**, K. V. Vamsi, R. Seshadri, and T. M. Pollock, Antiphase boundaries within B2 intermetallics: proximate structures, formation energies, and chemical stability, *In preparation*.
- 10. **J. A. Mayer** and Ram Seshadri, Electron count dictates phase separation in Heusler alloys, *Phys. Rev. Mater.* **6** (2022) 054406 [doi]
- 9. E. E. Levin, D. A. Kitchaev, Y. M. Eggeler, **J. A. Mayer**, P. Behera, D. S. Gianola, A. Van der Ven, T. M. Pollock, and R. Seshadri, Influence of plastic deformation on the magnetic properties of Heusler MnAu<sub>2</sub>Al, *Phys. Rev. Mater* **5** (2021) 014408. [doi]
- 8. J. H. Martin, B. Yahata, **J. A. Mayer**, R. Mone, E. Stonkevitch, J. Miller, M. O'Masta, T. Schaedler, J. Hundley, P. Callahan, and T. Pollock, Grain refinement mechanisms in additively manufactured nanofunctionalized aluminum, *Acta Mater.* **200** (2020) 1022–1037. [doi]
- 7. A. Pramanik, J. A. Mayer, S. Patibandla, K. Gates, Y. Gao, D. Davis, R. Seshadri, and P. C. Ray, Mixed-dimensional heterostructure material-based SERS for trace level identification of breast cancer-derived exosomes, *ACS Omega* 5 (2020) 16602–16611. [doi]
- C. Lenardi, J. A. Mayer, G. Faraone, J. Cardoso, S. Marom, R. Modi, A. Podestá, S. Kadkhodazadeh, and M. Di Vece, Nanoscale induced formation of silicide around gold nanoparticles encapsulated in a-Si, *Langmuir* 36 (2020) 939–947. [doi]
- 5. J. Cardoso, S. Marom, **J. A. Mayer**, R. Modi, A. Podestá, X. Xie, M. A. van Huis, and M. Di Vece, Germanium Quantum Dot Grätzel-Type Solar Cell, *Phys. Status Solidi A*, **215** (2018) 1800570. [doi]
- 4. J. H. Martin, B. D. Yahata, E. C. Clough, **J. A. Mayer**, J. M. Hundley, and T. A. Schaedler, Additive manufacturing of metal matrix composites via nanofunctionalization, *MRS Commun.* 8 (2018) 297–302.[doi]
- 3. K. Davis, M. Vidmar, A. Khasanov, B. Cole, M. Ghelardini, J. A. Mayer, C. Kitchens, A. Nath, B. Powell, and O. T. Mefford, The effect of post-synthesis aging on ligand exchange activity of iron oxide nanoparticles, *J. Colloid Interface Sci.* 511 (2018) 374–382. [doi]
- 2. J. H. Martin, B. D. Yahata, E. C. Clough, R. D. Mone, **J. A. Mayer**, E. Stonkevitch, R. C. Schubert, J. A. Miller, J. M. Hundley, T. A. Schaedler, and T. M. Pollock, Recent advances in additive manufacturing of high strength 7000 series aluminum, *Adv. Mater. Processes* **176** (2018) 18–22. [doi]
- 1. J. H. Martin, B. D. Yahata, J. M. Hundley, J. A. Mayer, T. A. Schaedler, and T. M. Pollock, 3D printing of high-strength aluminium alloys, *Nature* **549** (2017) 365–369. [doi]

#### **Patents**

Nanoparticle composite welding filler materials, and methods for producing the same; B. Yahata, J. A. Mayer, and J. H. Martin. (March 30, 2021) US Patent 10960497.

Please see engineering.ucsb.edu/jmayer for the latest version of this document, including updated publications. Manuscripts in preparation are available upon request.